so recently I found myself thinking
about the question of net neutrality and
in thinking about this I was reminded of
a distinction that I first encountered
gosh maybe 20 years ago from Larry
Lessig between different ways that human
societies can go about constructing how
we do things together
specifically the distinction is between
laws norms and code so first I just lay
out that distinction is and then maybe
do a little bit of thinking about how it
can be applied this question of net
neutrality so so norms are the baseline
in many ways they're the the base
mechanism the human society is used to
condition the behavior of of members you
norm might be don't speak too loudly
when you're in a public place or a norm
might be you know always wear clothes
things like that and the basic idea is
that human beings are very sensitive for
obvious long term Aboriginal tribal
reasons to the the social esteem or
social censure of other members of the
tribe and so when we go about doing
things that are in violation of social
norms we receive some kind of social
Center and that inhibits our behavior
shame is actually an aspect of this
mechanic
and it as a consequence by the way norms
show up is a very powerful mechanism for
social behavioral management in small
tight-knit communities if we all grow up
in the same place we all grow up
together we all grow up sharing the same
norms on the one hand everybody more or
less understands what those norms are
and on the other hand people have more
agency in enforcing the norms and so as
a consequence the norms work out pretty
well whereas by contrast if we're in an
environment where let's say a very large
cosmopolitan city with a very
heterogeneous group of people I don't
want to flow through it where it's not
obvious that any person who you interact
with me even share the norms that you
have norms and being vastly less
important and
conditioning behavior there's still a
baseline of norms constantly but they
cover a much larger percentage of human
behaviors and for good and for ill I
mean there's whole critiques of small
towns and how it's low they can be and
then we come to loss so in the case of a
law we're looking at something which is
in some sense a relatively modern
invention we've been doing norms for
hundreds of thousands of years probably
actually more in the direction of small
digit millions you know laws we even
have an identification
Hammurabi's code the notion of creating
explicit code and in specific
enforcement mechanisms to again
condition human behavior and and I would
suggest that I guess Rome which was well
known for its explicit laws by sanity
and which is well known for its explicit
laws and then the modern era the
emergence of Republic's Constitution
Republic's which are founded on a
founding document in the domain of law
are some of the characteristics
societies where law has been central and
crucial and so laws as a situation where
there is some some explicit articulation
of what is appropriate behavior and some
mechanism for evaluating whether or not
somebody's violated the law and then
enforce it against those violations
pretty straightforward I think we're all
pretty familiar with that that modality
and if we extend that to include
regulatory agencies which i think is
necessary then we can say that the the
20th century I think it's been the
high-water mark of both the the
presentation of the penetration of law
into social life and it's sort of
specificity and nuance so with with the
ability to use regulation and regulatory
agencies we developed a you know quite
robust capacity for law to modulate
human behavior and again for good and
thrill and it has certainly succeeded in
certain ways and failed in other ways
which then brings us to the third
category now the third category is code
now code is omnipresent in the form of
the laws of nature so that which goes up
must come down as a nice
pithy example of code
and it shows up also in human design so
the way that we say design our urban
environments if there simply is not a
road here then driving here is if not
impossible it least difficult if there's
not a bridge then crossing the canyon
has certain conditions so oftentimes we
will perceive code is showing up in
biological or in architectural
constraints most for most of history and
sometimes it in fact is I think what
that's it you had to make it explicit
is simply implicit that we just accept
code as being well again the laws of
nature the context in which laws and
norms play out but his point is that
we've now entered into an era where we
have enough power and we live in such a
not just a built environment but a
fluidly built environment in the context
particular of software that code is now
coming into its own and so it's kind of
just put it in context by giving you a
simple example that includes all three
let's say that that that there is a
sense or a choice or a shared sentiment
that it turns out that if you park a car
on a hill if you don't park the wheels
point in the right way sometimes the car
will roll down the hill to disastrous
consequences and so we've decided that
it's a good idea to park your wheels a
certain movie park a car on a hill in
the land of norms this will show up as
it is just what you do and to violate
that norm will involve other people
sending you social signals that you've
done something wrong icky disgusting bad
maybe they put a flier underneath your
windshield wiper telling you that you're
doing bad things and they just keep it
dirty looks or whatever and all that of
norms this social feedback would be
enough to condition your behavior and
everybody would do the right thing
obviously in the modern driver we're all
familiar with the fact that this is
against the law in most places and so in
this case what ends up happening is that
first there's a law that you must do
this is codified in some fashion and
then if you fail to do it
the police are empowered to put the
piece of paper under your wig joke in
this case in the form of a ticket and it
comes associated not with dirty looks
but some kind of fine or possibly even
potentially jail time some sort of
forcement mechanism that is designed to
make it so that you make the mental
calculus of well it's more costly to run
the risk of getting caught and being
enforced against than it is to just do
the thing that the loss tells me to do
and so generally speaking everybody
chooses to do that through the law as
you do so it's a kind of a utilitarian
calculus Oliver Wendell Holmes model but
then you have code so in the code case
what ends up happening is you could
imagine say you have a Tesla car that
has a software control structure in it
some pretty robust AI and there's just a
code update that causes the car itself
by itself that when it finds itself
parked on a hill to turn the wheels the
right way so what's notable about code
is that on the one hand it has this
sensibility of ease that we don't have
to deal with enforcement we don't have
to deal with compliance it just it just
is just is the way that it is and so on
the one hand it's nice it's very very
easy on the other hand of course it is a
form of tyranny that is never really
ever going to show up in the lands of
laws or norms to to route around code
actually requires an enormous amount of
capacity you literally have to be able
to hack the software in your car to of
what this thing happening and so as
we're entering into the into the era of
code it is now crucial be mindful again
of the fate of the difference between
code or law and norms and the difference
in potential the different kinds of
things that we can do this simply cannot
be done at all in the world of laws or
norms and also the pitfalls the things
that happen when we are not careful Joe
Edelman for example has written
extensively on the degree to which we
are already very much known in the world
of code say for example in the ways that
we can interact as a consequence of the
architectural choices that were made by
designers living far away in the social
media structures or the you know the
phone app structures that we interact
with you know if you're if your app only
has comes up thumbs down then that just
constrains your behavior regardless of
your choice and very effectively I
should add
so then let's think about this in the
context of net neutrality on the one
hand recently there's been a major
change in the state of the law and I
noticed for example that that hooks up
with the AT&T corporation overtly called
on the Senate or Congress to formally
reregulate net neutrality to pull it out
of the hands of a regulatory agency and
codify it more fundamentally in the form
of law and you know this was the event
that brought this distinction to my mind
because honestly I sort of aesthetically
felt it was a little bit old-fashioned
to imagine that Congress and legislative
lawmaking is appropriate capable
effective in an attempted to solve this
problem and that it seems to me just
sort of intuitively that perhaps we
should more closely consider code as the
modality that is right here and how do
we do that so for example the code
approach would not be along the lines of
let's decide what good behavior is and
then and then regulate or articulate
that in some language well particularly
that in a law but rather how do we
actually design it into the architecture
itself so for example one could imagine
code in the net neutrality by creating a
very very decentralized physical
Internet where it would become
impossible for anyone to force people to
constrain their speech in some important
way just because the ability to route
around that kind of censorship in the
ability to route around that kind of
friction would just be intrinsically so
high because of the nature of the way
the network itself was architected that
you wouldn't need to regulate it it
would just be foolishly unnecessary and
this sort of stuff actually does exist
in certain circumstances you if you
observe for example the way that Bitcoin
was very carefully architected without
any access or capacity to use laws it
did actually have the ability to access
norms and that does show
but it is predominantly built around the
ability to use code to condition
behavior in this case it had to imagine
game theoretic models of how people
would make different choices around when
they would apply their resources to
mining and when would they defect and
how would you police in minna-san in
some sense the essence of Bitcoin is to
consider how does one build relatively
complex social systems almost
exclusively out of code and being as we
are in this era of code I would put it
to you to consider and to think about
how we can go about solving problems
like net neutrality using code why that
might be in fact not just the best and
maybe even the only way in the
contemporary environment moving as
rapidly as it does and how do we build
the collective skillfulness to do so
well recognizing the enormous hazards
that are associated with building things
into the laws of nature